Finding Aid for James B. Griffin Papers 1922-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- North American Archaeology Card Files, circa 1930s-1990s; 122 linear feet
  - Geographic Areas and Cultures
    - Illinois
      - Elemental
        - Ca 21, 23, and 24 -- Snyders (Box 186)
        - Moorehead Mounds -- Utica (Box 186)
        - Race Track Mound (Box 186)
        - Utica Mound Group 2
      - Middle Mississippi
        - Illinois Pottery Types (Box 186)
        - Jd1 (Box 186)
        - Jd2 (Box 186)
        - Ca226 (Box 186)
        - Ca1 (Box 186)
      - Monks Mound (Box 186)
      - Spoon River
        - Kingston (Box 186)
        - F14 (Box 186)
        - F34 (Box 186)
        - F47 (Box 186)
        - F49 (Box 186)
        - F664 (Box 186)
        - Crabo (Box 186)
        - F891 (Box 187)
        - F892 (Box 187)
        - F893 (Box 187)
        - F894 (Box 187)
        - F896 (Box 187)
        - F897 (Box 187)
        - Emmons (Box 187)
        - Berry (Box 187)
        - Rose Mound Group (Box 187)
        - Sc (Box 187)
        - Crabtree (Box 187)
      - Gordon-Fewkes
        - Kincaid (Box 187)
        - Mx1 (Box 187)
        - Mx4 (Box 187)
        - Mx9 (Box 187)
        - Pp2 (Box 187)
      - Snyders (Box 188)
      - Cahokia
        - Excavation Unit 1 (Box 189)
        - Excavation Unit 2 (Box 189)
        - Excavation Unit 3 (Box 189)
        - South Group (Box 189)
        - Madison
          - Powell Mound 2 -- 84 (Box 189)
          - Powell Mound 2 (Box 189)
        - St. Clair
          - French Village (11-S-14) (Box 189)
          - B.T. Washington Cemetery (11-S-19) (Box 189)
          - McCary (Box 189)
          - Mitchell (Box 189)
          - Cahokia Md51 Subzone F Trade (Box 189)
        - Cahokia Pottery (Box 189)
        - Faunal Record (Box 189)
        - Cahokia -- Perino (Box 189)
        - BBB Motor Site, Ms595 (Box 189)
        - Persons (Box 190)
        - Field Catalog (Box 190)
        - Cahokia -- General (Box 190)
        - Mound Types (Box 190)
        - Structures (Box 190)
        - Burials (Box 190)
        - Flint
          - Projectile Points (Box 190)
          - Drills (Box 190)
          - Scrapers (Box 190)
          - Knives (Box 190)
          - Hoes (Box 190)
          - Spades (Box 190)
          - Celts (Box 190)
          - Chisels (Box 190)
          - Picks (Box 190)
        - Ground Stone
          - Grooved Axes (Box 190)
          - Celts (Box 190)
          - Discoidals (Box 190)
          - Sharpening Stones (Box 190)
          - Saws (Box 190)
          - Cross-Hatched Tablets (Box 190)
          - Mortars (Box 190)
          - Ear Spools (Box 190)
          - Boat Stones (Box 190)
          - Pipes
        - Galena (Box 190)
        - Hematite (Box 190)
        - Copper (Box 190)
        - Misc. Stone (Box 190)
        - Shell Implements
          - Hoes (Box 190)
          - Spoons (Box 190)
          - Knives (Box 190)
        - Shell Ornaments
          - Disc Beads (Box 190)
          - Barrel Beads (Box 190)
          - Tubular Beads (Box 190)
          - Pendants (Box 190)
          - Columella (Box 190)
          - Gorgets (Box 190)
          - Marginella (Box 190)
          - Oliva (Box 190)
          - Dippers (Box 190)
        - Bone Implements
          - Awls (Box 190)
          - Decorated Awls (Box 190)
          - Needles (Box 190)
          - Projectile Points (Box 190)
        - Bone Ornaments
          - Disc Beads (Box 190)
          - Cylindrical Beads (Box 190)
          - Ear Spools (Box 190)
          - Perforated Canines (Box 190)
          - Perf. Deer Toes (Box 190)
        - Pottery
          - Discs (Box 190)
          - Ear Spools (Box 190)
          - Discoidals (Box 190)
          - Beads (Box 190)
          - Pipes (Box 190)
          - Trowels (Box 190)
        - Kunneman Mound, Ca10 and Ca11 (Box 190)
        - Ramey Elliot Group, Ca19, 20 and 21 (Box 190)
        - Edwards Mounds, Ca24 and 25 (Box 190)
        - James Ramey Mound, Ca33 (Box 190)
        - Sawmill Mound, Ca39 (Box 190)
        - Moorehead Mound, Ca41 (Box 190)
        - Powell Mound, I46 (Box 190)
        - Thos. Ramey, Ca48 (Box 190)
        - Red Mound, Ca49 (Box 190)
        - Harding, Ca66 (Box 190)
      - Calhoun County
        - C.A. Knight Mound Group
          - Mound 1 (Box 190)
          - C2 (Box 191)
          - C3 (Box 191)
          - C4 (Box 191)
          - C5 (Box 191)
          - C6 (Box 191)
          - C7 (Box 191)
          - C8 (Box 191)
          - C9 (Box 191)
          - C10 (Box 191)
          - C14 (Box 191)
          - C16 (Box 191)
          - C17 (Box 191)
          - C19 (Box 191)
          - C21 (Box 191)
          - C22 (Box 191)
          - C25 (Box 191)
          - Knight Duplicate Material (Box 191)
      - Hopewell Pottery
        - Black Sand (Box 192)
        - Morton (Box 192)
        - Hopewell Zoned (Box 192)
        - Sumnerville (Box 192)
        - Norton (Box 192)
        - Baehr (Box 192)
        - Havana Cord Marked (Box 192)
        - Havana Plain (Box 192)
        - Havana Zoned (Box 192)
        - Snyders (Box 192)
        - Naples Stamped (Box 192)
        - Montezuma Punctate (Box 192)
        - Brangenberg (Box 192)
        - Weaver (Box 192)
        - Gooden (Box 192)
        - Unclassified (Box 192)
        - Crab Orchard (Box 192)
        - Raymond (Box 192)
        - Dillinger (Box 192)
    - Hopewell Bibliography
      - General (Box 193)
      - Hopewell in Adena Publicat. (Box 193)
      - Ohio (Box 193)
      - West Virginia (Box 193)
      - Southeast Hopewellian C. (Box 193)
      - New York, Penn. (Box 193)
      - Illinois (Box 193)
      - Indiana (Box 193)
      - Michigan (Box 193)
      - Iowa (Box 193)
      - Wisconsin (Box 193)
      - Missouri (Box 193)
      - Kansas (Box 193)
      - Minnesota (Box 193)
      - Richard G. Morgan's Hopewell Bibliographic Notes (Box 193)
    - Adena and Hopewell Notes
      - Indiana (Box 194)
      - Iowa (Box 194)
      - Ohio
        - Pottery -- Hopewell Mounds (Box 194)
        - Pottery -- Tremper Mound (Box 194)
        - Pottery -- Harness Mound (Box 194)
        - Pottery -- Mound City (Box 194)
      - Wisconsin (Box 194)
      - Illinois (Box 194)
      - West Virginia (Box 194)
      - Pennsylvania (Box 194)
      - Tennessee (Box 194)
      - Kentucky (Box 194)
      - Michigan (Box 194)
      - Oklahoma (Box 194)
      - Textiles (Box 194)
    - Pottery Decoration
      - Mazique Parallel Incised (Box 195)
      - Marksville (Box 195)
      - Coles Creek Horizontal Incised (Box 195)
      - Deasonville Red and White (Box 195)
      - Catahoulo Herringbone Incised (Box 195)
      - C.C. Rocker Stamp (Box 195)
      - Marksville Zoned Stamped (Box 195)
      - Wilkinson Fingernail Punctated (Box 195)
      - Fatherland Three-Line Incised (Box 195)
      - Caddo Maddox Finger-Trailed (Box 195)
      - Haley Ridged (Box 195)
      - Maddox Crosshatched Zoned Incised (Box 195)
  - Miscellaneous
    The Miscellaneous subseries includes mostly reference files, including listings of publications by Museum of Anthropology staff, mailing lists, and a set of Griffin's lecture notes on various topics.
    - P.F. Titterington Photos (Box 196)
    - Lectures and American Prehistory Bibliography
      - Miscellaneous (Box 197)
      - Eskimo (Box 197)
      - California (Box 197)
      - Historical (Box 197)
      - Eastern Siouan (Box 197)
      - Moheton (Box 197)
      - Tutelo (Box 197)
      - Offagoula (Box 197)
      - Mosopelea (Box 197)
      - Ohio (Box 197)
      - Shawnee (Box 197)
      - La Salle (Box 197)
      - Chiwere (Box 197)
      - Winnebago (Box 197)
      - Iowa (Box 197)
      - Oto (Box 197)
      - Missouri (Box 197)
      - Kansa (Box 197)
      - Dhegiha (Box 197)
      - Akansa-Quapaw (Box 197)
      - Ponka (Box 197)
      - Omaha (Box 197)
      - Osage (Box 197)
      - Mandan-Hidatsa (Box 197)
      - Catawba (Box 197)
      - Yuchi (Box 197)
      - Cherokee (Box 197)
      - Iroquois (Box 197)
      - Erie (Box 197)
      - Oniasont (Box 197)
      - Algonquian (Box 197)
      - Coiling (Box 197)
      - Stamping (Box 197)
      - Colanders (Box 197)
      - Weaving
      - Salt Pans (Box 197)
      - Asiatic Origin of Woodland (Box 197)
      - Physical Anthropology (Box 197)
      - Burial Terminology (Box 197)
      - Copper (Box 197)
      - Archaeology -- Methods (Box 197)
      - Southwest (Box 197)
    - Museum of Anthropology Faculty Publications
      - Staff Publications (Box 198)
      - K. Aga-Oglu (Box 198)
      - E.F. Greenman (Box 198)
      - J.B. Griffin
        - Co-Author (Box 198)
        - Book Reviews (Box 198)
        - In Press (Box 198)
      - V. Jones (Box 198)
      - V.W. Kinietz (Box 198)
      - G.K. Neumann (Box 198)
      - A.C. Spaulding (Box 198)
    - Address File (Box 198)
    - Course Registrations (Box 198)
    - Publication Mailing Records
      - Prehistoric Pottery of the Eastern United States (Box 199)
      - Individuals (Box 199)
      - Institutions (Box 199)
      - University of Michigan Students (Box 199)
      - University of Michigan Faculty (Box 199)
      - Foreign (Box 199)
      - Review (Box 199)
      - University of Michigan Students (Box 199)
      - Orient Interest (Box 199)
      - Annual Reports (Institutions) (Box 199)
      - Specific (Box 199)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 199)
      - General (Box 199)
      - Current Mailing List (Box 199)
    - Miscellaneous Ethnographic Notes and Resources (Box 200)
    - Miscellaneous Archaeological Photographs (Box 200)
  - Large Mounted Photographs
    The Large Mounted Photographs subseries includes photographs of sites and artifacts mounted on 8.5" by 11" cardboard, and is arranged geographically, mainly by state.
    - Alabama (Box 201)
    - Alaska (Box 201)
    - Arkansas
      - T.M.N. Lewis Collection (Box 201)
    - California (Box 201)
    - Colorado (Box 201)
    - Florida (Box 202)
    - Georgia (Box 202)
    - Illinois (Box 202)
    - Illinois (Box 203)
    - Indiana (Box 204)
    - Iowa (Box 204)
    - Kentucky (Box 204)
    - Maryland (Box 204)
    - Massachusetts (Box 205)
    - Michigan (Box 205)
    - Minnesota (Box 205)
    - Mississippi (Box 205)
    - Missouri (Box 205)
    - Nebraska (Box 206)
    - New Hampshire (Box 206)
    - New York (Box 206)
    - North Carolina (Box 206)
    - Ohio (Box 207)
    - Oklahoma (Box 207)
    - Pennsylvania (Box 207)
    - South Dakota (Box 207)
    - Tennessee (Box 208)
    - Texas (Box 208)
    - Utah (Box 209)
    - Virginia (Box 209)
    - Washington (Box 209)
    - West Virginia (Box 209)
    - Wisconsin (Box 209)
    - Wyoming (Box 210)
    - Southwest (Box 210)
    - Canada (Box 211)
    - Honduras (Box 211)
    - Mexico (Box 211)
    - Venezuela (Box 211)
    - U.S.S.R. (Box 212)
    - China (Box 212)
    - Japan (Box 212)
    - Pottery Making Series (Box 212)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 212)
  - Mississippi Valley Aerial Photographs
    The Mississippi Valley Aerial Photos subseries contains prints of index maps and photographs of the Mississippi Valley taken by the United States War Department. (Presumably Griffin used these as reference tools for his work in the Mississippi Valley.) The prints are arranged by quadrangle and flight.
    - P-4 Quadrangle, Greenbrier, Flights 1-9, 2 folders (Box 213)
    - Q-4 Quadrangle, Advance
      - Flights 1, 2, 3, 2 folders (Box 213)
      - Flights 4, 5, 6, 2 folders (Box 213)
      - Flights 7, 8, 9, 2 folders (Box 213)
      - Flights 10, 11, 12, 2 folders (Box 213)
    - R-4 Quadrangle, Morley
      - Flights 1, 2, 3, 2 folders (Box 213)
      - Flights 4, 5, 6, 2 folders (Box 213)
      - Flights 7, 8, 9, 2 folders (Box 213)
      - Flights 10, 11, 12, 2 folders (Box 213)
    - O-5 Quadrangle, Hendrickson
      - Flights 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 2 folders (Box 214)
    - P-5 Quadrangle, Puxico
      - Flights 1, 2, 3, 4, 2 folders (Box 214)
      - Flights 5, 6, 7, 8, 2 folders (Box 214)
      - Flights 9, 10, 11, 12, 2 folders (Box 214)
    - Q-5 Quadrangle, Bloomfield
      - Flights 1, 2, 3 (Box 214)
      - Flights 4, 5, 6, 2 folders (Box 214)
      - Flights 7, 8, 9, 2 folders (Box 214)
      - Flights 10, 11, 12, 2 folders (Box 214)
    - Index Maps, 2 folders (Box 215)
- Photographs, circa 1920s-1990s
  (with some older photographs)
  While photographs can be found throughout the papers (particularly in the North American Archaeology Card Files series), the Photographs series, ca. 1920s-1990s (0.25 linear feet) contains an accumulation of Griffin's more personal professional photographs. Prominent subjects includes Griffin portraits, Griffin and other archaeologists at various sites and conferences, Museum of Anthropology staff members, and the Radiocarbon Laboratory. In some instances correspondence providing context for particular photographs has been included.
  - James B. Griffin
    - Portraits, circa 1960-1985 (Box 216)
    - Candids and Group Shots, circa 1931-1993; 2 folders (Box 216)
  - Conferences, circa 1931-1980; 2 folders (Box 216)
  - Conferences -- International Congress of Americanists, 1902 (Box 216)
    (includes photos and signatures)
  - Museum of Anthropology Staff and Buildings, circa 1920s-1970s; 2 folders (Box 216)
  - Radiocarbon Laboratory, circa 1957 (Box 216)
  - Sites, circa 1931-1980s (Box 216)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1980s (Box 216)